前情提要
我们被袭击
We've been attacked.
你有什么感觉
How does that make you feel?
我感到害怕
I'm scared.
所以现在我们在表面上 最应该展现的是力量
Which is why the best face we can project outward now is one of strength.
-你做了什么  -你不能留在这里
-What have you done? -You can't be here.
别反抗 保持冷静 你可以呼吸的
Don't fight it. Keep calm. You can breathe.
新的黎明刚醒来
The new Dawn, just awoken.
-有什么不对劲 -出了什么问题吗
-Something's wrong. -Something wrong?
只是有种奇怪的感觉 我去边界附近走走
Just a weird feeling. I'm gonna walk the perimeter.
这些可是护卫舰 武装飞船
Those are corvettes. Gunships.
通讯浮标没有回应 失去信号了
Comms buoy's not responding. It's gone dark.
这一定与穹窿有关 空域正在扩大
It's gotta be connected to the Vault. The null field's expanding.
第二天 安纳克里昂人就出现了
And the very next day, the Anacreons showed up.
（改编自艾萨克阿西莫夫的小说）
曾经有一个男人 拜访哈里谢顿 请他告知自己的命运
Once, a man came to Hari Seldon and asked to be told his fate.
他想知道
He wanted to know
预测模型是否能测量他人生的重要性
whether the predictive models could chart the significance of his life.
但哈里告诉他 只有一群人的行为能被预测
But Hari told him only the movements of masses could be predicted.
个人的命运将永远是一个谜
The fate of one individual will always remain a mystery.
文明的构造
The clockwork of civilization…
文化的兴起与消亡
the rise and fall of cultures…
因果与世界
causes and worlds…
对于这些问题 哈里谢顿早已解开谜底
These were answers Hari Seldon had long since unriddled.
信仰是一种强大的武器
Belief is a powerful weapon.
正因如此 帝国才这么忌惮哈里的预测
That's why the Empire feared Hari Seldon's predictions so much.
大帝们统治着世俗事物 但身后事呢 我们的灵魂呢
Empires govern worldly concerns, but what comes after? Our souls?
这些属于信仰范畴
These realms are the purview of faith.
而信仰是在永恒之火中铸造的宝剑
And faith is a sword forged in the fires of the infinite.
大帝 你需要换种娱乐吗
Empire? Do you seek different amusement?
你就足够了 常规的方式、常规的欢愉
You'll do. For the routine pleasures in the routine manner.
你喜欢哪种欢愉 大帝
Which pleasures do you prefer, Empire?
你能提供虚无的欢愉吗 那有可能吗
Do you offer the pleasure of nothing? Is that on the menu?
他们说的是真的吗 谁都不能碰你
Is it true? No one's allowed to touch you?
你的胆子挺大的啊
Bold, aren't you?
我只有24个小时来服侍你 我想好好利用
I have only 24 hours of service to you. I want to make the most of it.
那你试一下触摸我吧
Then try to touch me.
我让你试一下
I said try.
光环能阻挡动能
The aura repels kinetic energy.
再试一次 这一次动作轻柔一点
I want you to try it again, with a softer touch.
慢一点
Slower.
那么…
So, how…
其他部分呢
…does the rest work?
怎么了
What?
有事需要你务必出席 大帝
You are required, Empire.
我明白大帝此刻有肢体亲密接触的需求
I understand Empire has a physiological need for intimacy.
但当前事宜的重要性超出这一需求
But the current matter supersedes this need.
使者赞沃
Ambassador Thanwall.
至高无上的大帝 荣耀之光…
Most esteemed Empire, glory to the light--
有话直说吧 使者
Out with it, Ambassador.
比邻星教宗欧珀去世了 大帝
Proxima Opal has passed, Empire.
节哀
Our condolences.
节哀 真诚致哀
Condolences. Heartfelt.
谢谢 大帝
Thank you, Empire.
比邻星教宗欧珀的教众将怀念及哀悼她
Proxima Opal will be missed and mourned by her flock.
主教团将提拔她的继任者玛泽菲尔格拉特
And now the conclave will elevate her successor, Zephyr Gilat.
一位有能力的候选人 我们喜欢她
A capable candidate. We like her.
使者 请转达我们的哀悼
Carry our condolences forward, Ambassador.
并告知格拉特 川陀永远欢迎她的来临
And inform Gilat she's always welcome on Trantor.
关于继任者 大帝
On the topic of a successor, Empire,
存在一些争议
there is some debate.
另一位候选人的呼声颇高
Another candidate has been gaining support.
泽菲尔哈利玛
Zephyr Halima.
哈利玛伊法不遵从既成的教规
Halima Ifa does not adhere to accepted doctrine,
与过去的比邻星教宗不同
as have our previous proximas.
她倡导回到《元八开经》
She is advocating for a return to the Primary Octavo.
她是自寻死路吗
Is she suicidal?
这女人是谁 胆敢质疑我们的根基
Who is this woman to question our primacy?
请恕罪 大帝 我…
A-A-Apologies, Empire. I-I--
-你知道这事吗  -刚刚才知道
-Did you know about this? -Only moments ago.
欧珀的葬礼是什么时候
When is Opal's funeral?
两天后 大帝
Two days hence, Empire.
不要对他人提及今天的对话 我们很快会联系你
Say nothing of this conversation. We will contact you shortly.
前任比邻星教宗上位时 是我提供了帮助
I helped install the previous Proxima.
我会尽快去和主教团见面
I'll leave for the conclave as soon as possible.
这有必要吗 你不能用全息影像联络
Is that really necessary? Can't you just holo-cast yourself in?
这次不行
Not this time.
透光教有三万亿教徒 这次教会分裂需要我亲身处理
Luminism claims three trillion followers. This schism requires a personal touch.
《元八开经》是什么
What's the Primary Octavo?
是异教徒的经文 帝国前时代的
A heretical scripture. Pre-imperial.
它将灵魂与个人知觉连结起来
It directly links the soul to individuated sentience.
-那是什么… -个人知觉
-What does that mean-- -Individuated sentience.
思考 黎明兄弟
Think, Brother Dawn.
如果灵魂仅与一个独立个体有关
If a soul cleaves only to an individual being,
那么人们会质疑没有个体性的事物
that calls into question that which cannot be individuated.
所有克里昂大帝 都是一世的完美基因复刻品
All Cleons are perfect genetic copies of the first.
因此…
And therefore…
我们没有灵魂
We don't have souls.
所以这个叫哈利玛的女人是说我们…
So, this Halima woman is saying we're, what?
没有人性
Not human?
间接的意思是这样 但…
Indirectly. But--
如果星系的民众开始认为
And if the galaxy comes to believe
领袖不如他们 而不是比他们更优越
their leaders are less than, rather than more than themselves,
民众也许不会再追随帝国
they may cease to follow.
我们是一艘玻璃船
We are a glass vessel…
由一只灵巧的手控制
spun with a fine hand.
如果内部压力开始紊乱并且我们不团结
If the pressures inside start to swirl and we are not uniform…
我们也许会爆炸
we may burst.
-你是谁  -塞佛哈定
-Who are you? -Salvor Hardin.
端点星的守卫者
Warden of Terminus.
安纳克里昂人不得进入帝国的领土
Anacreons aren't allowed on imperial soil.
你来这里做什么
What are you doing here?
拾荒
Scrapping.
很少看见拾荒者披盔戴甲
That's a lot of armor for scrappers.
我们在找这艘船的导航模组
We're looking for the ship's navigation module.
这艘废船上的任何关键部件 早在数十年前就被拆走了
Any critical components were stripped from this hulk decades ago.
不过一位真正的拾荒者会知道这点
But, again, a real scrapper would know that.
你应该离开 趁帝国还未得知此事
You should leave. Before the Empire catches wind of this.
我族人并不畏惧帝国
My people do not fear the Empire.
听着 你们没想到会碰到我
Look, I caught you by surprise
所以你们在临时想办法
and now you're improvising.
但如果你们要杀我 你们早就动手了
But if you were gonna kill me, you would have already.
接下来的计划是
So what's the play?
那座塔 带我们去那里
That tower. Take us there.
为什么
Why?
我还是说清吧 守卫者
Let me be clear, Warden.
我们知道如何利用一切可用的资源
We know how to use every resource we come across.
我们早前观察那几个孩子
The children we observed earlier,
我们看到他们在黎明前夕偷偷溜走
we've seen how they sneak away just before dawn,
远离了你们其他人
straying far away from the rest of your flock.
如果你不带我们去那座塔 我们只需利用其中一个孩子就行 很简单
If you won't lead us to the tower, we'll simply utilize one of them.
没那么简单 那里有围栏
It's not that simple. We have a fence.
我们知道你们有围栏
We're aware of your fence.
我们看到你之前在那里进行维护工作
We saw you perform maintenance on it earlier.
所以你是带我们穿越围栏的完美人选
Which makes you the perfect person to take us through it.
那就去塔那里吧
To the tower then!
我们在围栏上使用了基因识别技术
The fence uses DNA recognition.
任何不在数据库里的人都会被辐射击中
It'll radiate anyone who isn't in the database.
我可以带一个人进去
I might be able to get one of you in.
如果我们一起穿越
If we walk through together,
围栏会将第二人视作系统错误
the fence should write off the second person as an error.
那就带我们所有人进去
Then take us all through it.
这招只能用一次 可能吧
This only works once. Maybe.
我过去曾拖进围栏的生物已经死了
The only thing I've ever dragged through this fence was already dead.
我能感到你的紧张 别紧张
I can feel you tensing up. Don't.
如果她在这一轮值班结束前没回来 我们会夷平你的城市
If she isn't back within a watch, we'll raze your city to the ground.
去 叫上其他人
Go. Get the others.
建立一个防线 别让人看见
Establish a perimeter and stay out of sight.
你来驾驶 我拿枪
Wanna drive and I'll hold the gun?
至少告诉我你的名字吧
Tell me your name, at least.
我们成了好朋友了
Are we best friends now?
你冒很大的险来这里
You've risked a lot coming here.
我们赌上了一切 守卫者
We've risked everything, Warden.
-不 前方路上有个男孩 -别耍花招 我有眼睛
-No. There was a boy in our path! -Don't get cute. I have eyes.
塔在那边
The tower's that way.
这是捷径 这条路的守卫比较少
I'm taking a shortcut. Fewer watchmen this way.
那是什么
What is that?
停下
Stop.
关于塞佛哈定的那些传说  通常从这里开始
The stories about Salvor Hardin? They usually begin here.
守卫者与幽灵
The warden and the ghost,
令人费解地紧密联系在一起
inexplicably bound together.
谢谢
Thanks.
他们是怎么避开我们的雷达的
How did they slip past our radar?
也许是按低空航线飞进来的
Flew in the nap of the earth. Maybe.
有他们飞船的踪迹吗
Any sign of their ships?
他们自称为拾荒者 说他们在找导航模组
They claimed to be scrappers. Said they were after a navigation module.
-明显的谎言 -我们必须联络帝国
-Obviously bullshit. -We need to contact the Empire.
未经授权 我们不能做任何事
We can't do anything without authorization.
拜托 妈妈 我们只是名义上的帝国哨站
Come on, Mom. We're an imperial outpost in name only.
他们上一次联络我们是哪年哪月  十年前了吧
When was the last time they even contacted us? A decade ago?
他们不会保护我们的 我们必须自己来
They won't defend us. We need to do it ourselves.
别急 暴力是无能者…
Easy. Violence is the last refuge--
最后的庇护所 我知道 那是老人之言
Of the incompetent, I know. That's an old man's doctrine.
那是我比你更年轻时观察所得的道理
It's an observation I made when I was younger than you.
在哈里的计划中 我们会等待帮助还是独立行动
Would Hari's plan have assumed we'd wait for help or act on our own?
哈里已经不在这了 妈妈 我们必须自救
Hari is not here, Mom. We need to help ourselves.
欢迎醒来 我的好朋友
Welcome back, best friend.
我们正要加深对彼此的了解时你就昏迷了
You left the conversation just as we were really getting to know each other.
头疼 感觉牙齿要掉了
Headache? Teeth feel like they're falling out?
那该死的东西是什么
What was that cursed thing?
我们对端点星殖民时它就在了
It was here when we colonized Terminus.
我们在扫描时没探测到它 我猜你们也没有
Didn't show up on any of our scans. I guess it didn't show up on yours either.
为什么你没有受影响
Why did it not affect you?
只能说我是你在端点星上最不想碰到的人
Let's just say I'm the last person on Terminus you wanted to come across.
所以…
So…
然后呢 守卫者
what now, Warden?
她带了一支小规模军队
She had a small army with her.
还有他们的脚印 有的很深
An-- And their tracks, some of them were deep.
步幅较短 好像他们在搬运沉重的设备
Shorter stride lengths. As if they were carrying heavy equipment.
他们似乎计划在此驻留 爸爸
Like they're planning on digging in, Dad.
-你想怎么做  -不知道
-Well, what do you wanna do? -I don't know.
我一直遵从我的直觉 但…
I've been following my instincts, and--
我不知道 也许那只是碰巧走运
I don't know, maybe it was just dumb luck.
你的直觉不仅仅带你上了飞船
Your instincts didn't just lead you to the ships.
而且让你找到了她 你阻止了她
They led you to her. And you stopped her.
如果你数学更好的话
If you were better at math,
你就会知道反复而来的运气 就绝不仅是运气 塞佛
you'd know that repeated luck was more than just luck, Salvor.
无论你母亲是否愿意承认
Whether your mother wants to admit it or not,
自从你学会走路起 我们一直跟着你的行为做事
we have been following your lead from the moment you pulled yourself upright.
人们选你担任守卫者是有原因的
It's no accident the people made you warden.
所以 带领我们吧
So lead us.
很荣幸初次见到您 大帝 有何可为您效劳
I have never had the pleasure, Empire. How may I be of service?
你是欧布雷特队长
Captain Obrecht, is it?
阴影师 大帝 阴影师欧布雷特
Shadowmaster, Empire. Shadowmaster Obrecht.
非常相像
A fine likeness.
处理有问题的宫殿人员 规程是什么
What's the protocol for dealing with a problem palace attendant?
请问是哪个级别的人员
What level of attendant, if I may ask?
-在花园工作的人 -我能问是哪类问题吗
-Someone who works in the garden. -May I ask the nature of the problem?
不能 我只需要她的名字
You may not. I just want her name.
没问题 大帝 若还需要什么 也可以交代我
I can ascertain that, Empire. Along with anything else you may require.
暂时只有这个
That's all for now.
我看到围栏外至少有十几个安纳克里昂人
I saw at least a dozen Anacreons outside the fence.
特拉维克 从南边的环圈靠近
Travik, take the southern loop.
凯林 你负责西边
Kalin, cover the west.
叶特 你守在东边 监控有没有人从那个山脊过来
Yate, I want you on the east so you can spot anyone coming over that ridge.
如果看到那些人 我们该做什么
And if we see any of these guys, what are we supposed to do?
什么都不做
Nothing.
别向他们开枪 别跟他们说话 观察他们 随时向我汇报情况
Don't shoot at them, don't speak to them. Just watch 'em and keep me informed.
-端点星出现安纳克里昂人是怎么回事  -她叫法拉
-What's this about Anacreons on Terminus? -Calls herself Phara.
除此之外 她的故事完全说不通
Beyond that, nothing about her story adds up.
你最擅长看出别人是否在撒谎了
If anyone can tell whether somebody's lying, it's you.
问题就是这个 我看不出她在撒谎
That's just the thing. I can't tell if she's lying
还是不说实情
or if she's just not telling the truth.
两者有差别吗
Is there a difference?
我有个计划 但我需要你的帮助
I've got a plan. But I'm gonna need your help.
这是做什么 虐囚
What's this? Torture?
他是我的男仆从
He's my manservant.
为我跑腿 在需要的时候帮我的靴子封边
Runs and fetches. Reseals my boots when they need it.
我猜对我野外的同伴来说 这一轮值班已经结束了
I'm thinking a watch has passed, as far as my weald-men are concerned.
你到底为何来这里 法拉
Why are you really here, Phara?
塞佛很擅长读人心
Salvor has a talent for reading people.
准得吓人 我刚才还和她母亲聊起
It's uncanny, really. I was just telling her mother about it.
她不相信你
She doesn't believe you.
你刚告诉她你是我的上司 这下我像在拍马屁了
Well, you told her you're my boss. Now my praise rings hollow.
你对基地塔为何感兴趣
What's your interest in the Foundation Tower?
因为模组 我已经告诉你了 你总是问我相同的问题
The module. I already told you. You keep asking me the same questions.
我是在给你机会 让你回答得更好
I'm giving you a chance to give better answers.
正面
Crowns.
我知道你在找别的东西
I know you're after something else.
我们没有任何安纳克里昂文物 也没有重型武器 所以到底…
We don't have any Anacreon artifacts, no heavy weapons, so what--
我们在原地绕圈
This is going in circles.
解释给她听
Explain it to her.
把她想要的给她吧
Just give her what she wants.
你的口音不算糟
Your accent's not terrible.
你显然是向港口城市的人学的
You were taught by someone in the port city, obviously.
懒元音
Those lazy vowels.
我是贸易商
I'm a trader.
我偶尔与你们星球的人做生意
I do business with your people now and then.
怪不得从你身上 我嗅到了狄斯比斯人的味道
Thought I smelled a whiff of Thespin on you.
我要导航模组 仅此而已
I want the navigation module. That's it.
又是一个谎言
Another lie.
你也说安纳克里昂语
You speak Anacreon as well?
一个字都不懂
Not a word.
-但你知道我在撒谎  -反面
-Yet you know I'm lying? -Cats.
概率是二分之一
That was a 50-50 chance.
又是反面 你到底是谁
Cats again. Who are you really?
概率是四分之一
Twenty-five percent chance there.
又回到正面了
Now it's back to crowns.
八分之一了 又一个正面 你为什么来这里
Twelve and a half percent. And another crown. Why are you here?
又是正面
Another crown again.
我可以把概率告诉你 但是反复而来的运气绝不是运气
I'd give you the percentage, but repeated luck is never luck.
你是谁
Who are you?
我们是拾荒者 为找模组而来
We're scrappers. The module.
你们不是拾荒者 导航模组不过是为了转移…
You're not scrappers. And the navigation module's a distraction--
别再玩这些幼稚的把戏了
Enough of these child games.
把这个狄斯比斯暴徒的链子解开 让他直接动手吧
Take this Thespin thug off his leash and let him get on with it!
你的疤痕…
Your scars…
蟹足肿
keloids.
你的左眼…
Your left eye…
纳米玻璃
nano-glass.
你是在帝国轰炸安纳克里昂时 失去左眼的吧
You lose it when the Empire bombed Anacreon?
你当时应该是五、六岁
I imagine you must have been, what, five, six at the time?
中子弹的爆发力较低 但是电离辐射的能量很高
Neutron bombs have a low explosive yield but a high amount of ionizing radiation.
我知道大约一半的人口一周内就死去了
Now, I know about 50% of the population died off within a week,
另外的两、三成人在那一年里死去
another 20 or 30 within the remaining year.
你很可能在那次轰炸后 成为孤儿了 对吧
Odds are you came out the other end an orphan, right?
也许失去了爸妈
Probably lost a mom and dad.
活活地被烧死
Boiled alive.
也许是慢性死亡
Or maybe s-slower.
癌症
Cancer.
你的母亲是甲状腺癌 她的嗓音在死前变了
Thyroid for your mother. Her voice, it changed before she died.
你还失去了谁 姐妹
Who else did you lose? A sister?
一个兄弟
A brother.
一个弟弟
A little brother.
她的内心有一种死亡的气息 就像…
There's a deadness inside her. It's like a--
没有底的井 将一切吸入
It's like a well with no bottom, just sucking everything in.
她想死
She wants to die.
她想让所有人死 我感觉到了
She wants everyone to die. I felt it.
她在崩溃时说了什么 你听懂了吗
What she said when she broke, did you understand any of it?
听懂了一些 是古安纳克里昂语 不是通用语
Some, yeah. It's archaic Anacreon, not the common vernacular.
她说漏嘴了 因为我也听懂了一些话
Well, she slipped up. Because I understood something too.
一个我曾在全息影像见过的名字 拉肯柯恩
A name I remember from the holos. Larken Keaen.
在安铎星带纠纷事件时
During the Anthor Belt dispute,
安纳克里昂和狄斯比斯为帝国带去贡礼
Anacreon and Thespis brought gifts to the Emperor.
我族人带的是《洗礼经》
My people's was the Book of Ablut--
安纳克里昂的是一把 为其最伟大猎手雕刻的弓
And Anacreon's was a bow carved for its greatest hunter.
-拉肯柯恩 -意思是
-Larken Keaen. -Meaning?
法拉不是什么捡垃圾的
Phara's not just some junker.
她是安纳克里昂的大猎手
She's the Grand Huntress of Anacreon.
这一切动乱到底是谁造成的
All this unrest, who's responsible for it?
堕落者 这是一个化名
Sinkers. A nom de guerre.
77层的热沉室熔化后 那是星桥坠落造成的
After the heat sink meltdown on level 77. It was caused when the Star Bridge fell.
35年后 我们仍在处理这件事的余波
And 35 years later we're still grappling with the aftereffects.
大帝的职责就是 处理一堆相互竞争优先级的事项
The businesses of Empire is a cascade of competing priorities.
我和主教团会面时 白昼兄弟将会需要你的帮助
Brother Day will need your support while I tend to the conclave.
公务太繁多
It's overwhelming.
对于一个人而言
For one man.
幸运的是我们有三个人
Fortunately, there are three of us.
坏事往往成三 你听说了吗 兄弟
Bad tidings also come in threes. Have you heard the news, Brother?
大角星区有一个通讯浮标断联了
A communications buoy in the Arcturus Sector has come off-line.
那些浮标应该常常断联吧
They must go off-line all the time, right?
我们大概有几千个浮标遍布整个星系
We probably have thousands of them across the galaxy.
数万个
Tens of thousands.
但只有那个浮标负责外围星域的通讯
But only one that handles communications in the Outer Reach.
你没有理解此事的严重性
I see that you fail to grasp the significance.
是端点星
It's Terminus.
黄昏兄弟将哈里谢顿的信徒流放到那里
It's where Brother Dusk exiled Hari Seldon's followers.
外围星域、主教团、叛变
The Reach. The conclave. Insurgency…
你看出这一系列事情的规律了吗
Do you see a pattern forming here?
给他们看看
Show them.
感知到你们的脆弱后 很快将有其他力量 开始对帝国进行破坏
Sensing vulnerability, soon other players will begin to apply downward pressure.
银河中某个主要的宗教必然会发起煽动
An exhortation from one of the galaxy's major religions is a given.
也可能是川陀本地发起的起义
Or perhaps a homegrown insurrection here on Trantor.
如果灭亡的速度可以加快 那可以减慢吗
If the fall can be accelerated, can it not also be slowed?
瞧瞧你现在 兄弟
Now look at you, Brother.
坐在中央王座上 刚愎自用的样子
So smugly self-assured atop the middle throne.
我以前会在镜子前练习这个笑容
I used to practice that smile in the mirror.
够了 我知道这一幕的结局
Enough. I know how the scene ends.
但你领会了其中的教训吗
But have you embraced its lessons?
透光教 如今堕落者起义了
Luminism. The Sinker insurrection happening now.
谢顿几乎给你列了一份待做事项清单
Seldon all but drew you a to-do list.
你却完全无视
And you ignored him.
因为他是个江湖骗子
Because he was a charlatan.
你没有任何新的创造
You offer nothing new.
不过是一个更嫩的葡萄
Just a younger grape…
来自同一个葡萄藤
from the same vine,
注定酿成同样的酒
destined for the same old bottle.
你们无法拯救自己
You can't save yourselves…
但你们能拯救功业 传承后世
but you can save your legacy.
哈里谢顿已死去多时
Hari Seldon is long dead.
而且是被自己的学徒杀死的
Murdered by his protégé, no less.
人是死了 但是阻止得了起义吗 兄弟
The man was murdered. But what about the movement, Brother?
烈士的影响力往往超越其本身的生命长度
Martyrs tend to have a long half-life.
因为你 我们所看到的是 一个真正的外交危机的开始
Thanks to you, we are now staring down the barrel of a genuine diplomatic crisis.
我该做什么 路易斯
What was I supposed to do, Lewis?
让法拉杀了我 然后对孩子们动手
Let Phara kill me and then move on to the kids?
你不该在我不在场的情况下拷问她
You shouldn't have questioned her without me.
你应庆幸 我们知道她的身份了
Be glad I did. We know who she is now.
我们有筹码了 可以与她的同伴讨价还价
We have leverage. We can bargain with her people.
如果这个选择让全城陷入暴动
If this choice inflames the city into violence,
你成功让我们如此高明地自取灭亡
you have achieved elaborate suicide for us all.
哈里不是说基地会在 第一次危机中存活吗
Didn't Hari say the Foundation survives the first crisis?
没错 但正如我曾告诉你的 你是异类
Yes, he did. But, as I've told you before, you are an outlier.
-意思是  -塞佛
-Meaning? -Salvor.
意思是计算结果不包括你
Meaning that you weren't accounted for.
你与穹窿有一种联结
You have a connection with the Vault
而那是不可能被预测的
which couldn't have possibly have been predicted.
模型中没有你
You are not baked into the model.
意思是我不属于上帝的计划
You're saying I'm not part of God's plan.
意思是心理历史学无法计算个人行为
I am saying psychohistory can't account for individuals.
所以你是说我毁了上帝的计划
So you're saying I've destroyed God's plan?
-是时候后退一步了 塞佛 -退一步
-It's time to take a step back, Salvor. -Step back?
我以为基地存在的全部意义
I thought the whole damn point of the Foundation
在于为难以预料的情况做准备
was preparing for the unthinkable.
在我要求更多防御武器时
When I asked for more defensive weapons,
你说袭击的可能性极低
you said the likelihood of an attack seemed remote.
在我提出进行更多军事训练时 没人回应
When I wanted to run more drills, nothing.
结果我们走到这一步 毫无准备
So here we are now, not prepared.
也许我是异类 但搞砸计划的不是我 路易斯
I might be an outlier, but I'm not the one screwing up the Plan, Lewis.
这是总督路易斯皮仁恩
Lewis Pirenne, director.
安纳克里昂议事会为什么派最高级的军官
Now, why would the Anacreon Council send its highest-ranking military officer
到一个帝国哨站
to an imperial outpost?
这是你们的末日邪教伪装出来的门面吗
Is that what you're pretending your little doomsday cult is?
因为我在这里看不见帝国的影子
Because I don't see the Empire anywhere.
我只看到学者、劳工和极少的枪械
All I see are academics, laborers and very few guns.
你们破坏了通讯浮标
You took down the comms buoy.
当然 我们想暗中行动 避开监控
Of course. We wanted to operate in private, away from prying eyes.
你要明白帝国最终会派人来调查的
You have to know the Empire will send someone to investigate eventually.
还是说那就是你的意图
Or is that the point?
你们这里的女性比男性聪明多了
Your women are so much sharper than your men.
蛮族王国被流放了 你们没有理由来这里
The barbarian kingdoms are exiled. You have no business here.
“蛮族”
"Barbarians."
不过是个用在异类身上的 歧视词语 真是方便
Just a convenient slur for anyone not like you.
川陀让我们在这里自生自灭 你的人和我的人
Trantor left us all here to die. Your people and mine.
我们不过是以不同的速度灭亡
We're just dying at different speeds.
基地没有灭亡
The Foundation isn't dying.
我们要完成哈里谢顿托付我们的任务
We are fulfilling the mission Hari Seldon entrusted us with.
谢顿也预测到灭亡将会从银河边缘开始
Seldon also predicted that the fall would begin at the edge of the galaxy.
-这里 -同样的科学计算
-Here. -The same science
在星桥坠落时拯救了帝国宫殿
that saved the Imperial Palace when the Star Bridge fell
也保护着端点市
protects Terminus City.
你是说你的能量屏障
You mean your energy barrier?
武器的效用取决于使用者的能耐
A weapon's only as good as the man who's wielding it.
凯林 你那边情况如何
Kalin, what's your situation?
这里的人越来越多了
It's getting pretty crowded over here.
-我可能需要支援 -不可能
-I think I need backup. -Not happening.
塞佛看到十几个人 你是说 到处都是安纳克里昂人
Salvor saw a dozen. You're telling me we've got Anacreons all over?
我是说我看到他们携带的枪械 足以将整座城夷为平地
I'm telling you I'm seeing enough guns to take out the whole town.
大帝
Empire.
我们讨论的问题
The matter we discussed?
她叫阿祖拉欧蒂利 13岁起成为宫殿植物学家
Her name is Azura Odili. A palace botanist since the age of 13.
她的父亲已身故 生前也是花园的农业生态学家
Her father, deceased, was also an agroecologist in the gardens.
她的母亲创办了一所插花学校 目前已关闭了
Her mother founded a school for the ikebana, now closed.
你是说有什么问题吗
You said there was a problem?
在这种情况下通常怎么解决问题
How are problems generally solved in this situation?
只要能达到目的就可以 我的职责是让问题消失 大帝
Any manner that achieves its goal. My job is to eliminate problems, Empire.
阿祖拉欧戴利
Azura Odili.
欧迪利 欧德利
Oh-dee-lee? Oh-dih-lee?
蒂 大帝
Dee, Empire.
你之前在我的寝宫外
You were outside my chambers earlier.
-我想知道你认为自己看见了什么 -我什么都没看见 大帝
-Want to know what you think you saw. -I saw nothing, Empire.
不 我认为你看见了一些东西
No. I believe you saw something.
我只看见大帝希望我看见的
I only see what Empire wants me to see.
我可以罢免你的职务
I could have you removed from your station,
送你去80层清理热沉室
sent to scrub the heat sinks on level 80.
我可以对你下狠手 远比这更狠
I could do worse to you. Much worse.
你很清楚
You know all this.
大帝 黄昏兄弟让我来请你过去
Empire, Brother Dusk has asked me to summon you.
告诉他我马上过去
Tell him I'm coming.
把这个花圃都移除
Remove this entire bed.
在我的寝宫 花的香气太浓郁了
From my chambers the smell of the blossoms is overbearing.
-大帝 这种事不需要你… -已经解决了 你走吧
-Empire, you needn't bother with this-- -It's settled. You can go.
狼息叶有助缓解疼痛
Wolvesbreath helps with the pain.
是带红色条纹的褐绿色叶子
The brownish-green leaves with the red stripe.
它们能缓解肿胀和淤伤…
They reduce the swelling and bruising--
我不记得向你征求医疗建议
I don't recall asking for your medical advice.
是哪种
Which?
尖叶
The pointed leaves.
这是什么
What is it?
狼灵属
Lupi spiritus.
这是狼息叶 大帝 来自我们的草药园
Wolvesbreath, Empire. From our medicinal garden.
是一种镇痛剂和血管舒张药
It's an analgesic and vasodilator.
有毒吗
Is it poisonous?
没有 狼息叶可以泡茶或酿药酒
No. Wolvesbreath is used in tea as well as tinctures.
它能刺激血管、促进康复…
It stimulates the blood vessels, promotes healing--
吃下去
Eat it.
如果接下来的几个小时你没死
If you're not dead within the next few hours,
就送1公斤到我的寝宫来
have a kilogram of these sent to my quarters.
是 大帝
Of course, Empire.
雷洛弗拉姆 马上回家
Laylo Fulham, get your ass back home this instant!
他们会突破吗
Are they gonna get through?
当然不会
Course not.
大家都回家去 拜托了 这里不安全 快后退…
Go back to your home, people. Please. It's not safe out here. Back up. Back up.
你们必须立即离开
You need to come out here. Now.
我挺忙的 叶特
Kind of busy here, Yate.
我知道 但我还是要打给你
I know, and I'm still calling.
安纳克里昂军队在东边、西边、南边集结
We've got Anacreon's troops massing from the east, west, south,
估计北边也有
and presumably the north.
还记得怎么拿枪吗 老头
Remember how to hold a rifle, old man?
枪管对着前方
Barrel goes forward?
我们在围栏外的多个地点 发现安纳克里昂人
We've spotted Anacreons at multiple locations outside the fence.
-我去西边 -我们去北边
-I'll go west. -We'll head north.
我不应该离开 路易斯完全不是对手
I shouldn't leave. Lewis is completely overmatched in there.
我会照顾他的 我保证
I'll babysit him, I promise.
好吧
All right.
是真的吗 里面有安纳克里昂的头目
Is it true? You got some kind of Anacreon chieftain in there?
你喝酒了吗 穆勒
You been drinking, Muller?
银河系要完蛋了 是吗  哈里的预测成真了
It's the end of the galaxy, isn't it? Hari's prediction's coming true.
你听到的是谣言 穆勒 只是一个本地的盗猎者
You got hold of a bad rumor, Muller. Local poacher's all.
他们已经到了 对吧
They're already here, aren't they?
嘿 不如你歇一下吧
Hey, why don't you just take a break for a second.
嘿
Hey!
我不会伤害你的
I won't hurt you.
告诉我你是谁
Just tell me who you are.
塞
Sal.
塞 嘿…怎么回事
Sal. Hey, hey. What's wrong?
我刚才在川陀的帝国图书馆
I was just in the Imperial Library on Trantor.
-什么叫你在那里  -我身处那里 在书架间
-What do you mean you were there? -I mean I was there. In the stacks.
天花板是木制的 还有很多大理石半身像
The ceiling was wooden, there were all these marble busts.
有个拿着刀的男孩
And there was a boy with a knife.
是带我找到安纳克里昂人的那个男孩
It was the same boy who led me to the Anacreons.
是穹窿 我能感觉到它 雨果 它想告诉我些什么
It's the Vault. I can feel it, Hugo. It's trying to tell me something
关于安纳克里昂人和这次危机 关于一切
about the Anacreons and this crisis. Everything.
好的 听我说 我过去总说 你应该离开这个星球
Okay, listen to me. I've always said you should let this planet shrug you off.
但看到你做的事 你竟能感知 法拉内心的想法
But watching you work, where you could sense what Phara was feeling inside…
这很特别
that's special.
塞 别的人不可能做到这点
Other people can't do that, Sal.
我对你有百分之百的信心
I have absolute faith in you.
你们中的谁是统计学大师提沃尔
Who among you is Master Statistician Tivole?
大帝 愿明光永不灭
Empire. May the light never dim.
愿明光永不灭
May the light never dim.
-你收到我的征询了 -是 大帝
-You received my query. -I did, Empire.
但我们尚未得到结果
But I can't say yet we have the results.
黄昏给你安排这项任务后已经过了多久
How long has it been since Dusk set you to this task?
30年
Three decades?
你在你那数字陵墓里都忙些什么
What do you do in your mausoleum of calculus
为何还没有结果
if not achieve results?
那就说进展吧 你有何进展
Progress, then. What is your progress?
我们认为哈里谢顿的预测模型 是违背事实的
We believe the-- the predictive models of Hari Seldon to be counterfactual.
为什么这么说
And you believe this why?
在谢顿发表他的异教学说后的35年来
In the 35 years since Seldon uttered his heretical proclamations,
帝国扩张了 而不是收缩 无论是以哪个重要的参数…
the Imperium has expanded, rather than contracted, by every critical metric--
够了
Stop.
谢顿的预言
Seldon's prophecies.
和我说说他的数学计算 这个“序数分析”
Speak to me of his math, this "ordinal analysis."
不过是一幅占卜牌
It's a spread of fortune teller's cards
谢顿选择将其诠释为神旨
which Seldon chose to interpret as divination.
他在回归模型中发现的证明 并没有证据所支持
The verification he found in the regression models is unsupported.
但是近期的种种事件怎么说
But what of these-- these recent events?
主教团 透光教
The conclave? Luminism?
毫无根据的猜想 同样是模糊而没有证据支持的
Baseless conjecture. Again, vague and unsupported.
任何人都能预测到回到正教这件事
I mean, anyone could predict a return to orthodoxy.
心理历史学只是老人空想出来的研究
Psychohistory is the fanciful work of an old man's imagination.
如果它并非老人空想出来的研究 那么是什么
If it weren't the fanciful work of an old man's imagination, what then?
研究最终被证为真实的概率是多少
What is the likelihood that it's all true? Every prophecy?
微小得可以忽略 大帝
Vanishingly small, Empire.
但不是零
But not zero.
对吗
Correct?
非零
Not zero?
你们到底是什么白痴
What kind of idiots are you?
一千个帝国数学家
A thousand imperial mathematicians…
却理解不了一个人的计算
…can't parse the numbers of one man?
所以银河系中没有任何人有办法
So there's nothing anyone in the galaxy can do?
这是你们交出的最佳结果
Is that what it is? Is that the best you've got?
告诉我…
Tell me. Tell me!
告诉我
Tell me!
在人生的晚年
In the twilight of a man's life…
当他的个人历史将近尾声时
…when his biography is nearly complete,
他开始绝望地想知道他的人生
he grows desperate to know the measure of his days…
他的声音与前人所有的声音相比结果如何
how his voice compares to the chorus of those who've come before.
我重要吗 我的选择是自己做出的吗
Do I matter? Are my choices my own?
我的命运是否被看不见的手所左右
Or is my destiny governed by an unseen hand?
白昼兄弟 来为我们送行
Brother Day. Come to see us off?
你的统计师们来找过我
I was paid a visit by your statisticians.
他们的计算结果如此自圆其说 真了不起
It's remarkable how self-reinforcing their results are.
我认为你最好还是留在川陀处理事务
I think it's best that you stay and tend to matters on Trantor.
大帝 第一克里昂从未离开过川陀
Empire, a primary Cleon has not left the bosom of Trantor
从一脉相承的王朝开始起就没有过
since the dawn of the Genetic Dynasty.
德默泽尔是对的
Demerzel is right.
我们订立这些规程是有原因的
We have these protocols in place for a reason.
我则认为我们的规程让我们懈怠了
And I say our protocols have made us complacent.
当年你和我现在一样坐在中央王座上
When you sat on the middle throne, as I do now,
讨论如何处理安纳克里昂和狄斯比斯时
and were debating what to do about Anacreon and Thespis,
我们该如何回应 你记得 你当时是怎么说的吗
what our response should be, do you remember what you said?
记得
I do.
仿佛是昨日
Like it was yesterday.
那时我七岁
I was seven.
我们最年长的兄弟认为应该恩赦
Our eldest brother had argued for a bout of grace.
你转向我说 “你如何看此事 初升的黎明 ”
You turned to me and said, "What do you think, Ascending Dawn?"
我知道你反对恩赦
I knew you were against grace,
你想轰炸蛮族王国
that you wanted to bomb the barbarian kingdoms.
但我很怕 我大胆说了出来
But I was scared. And I dared say so.
如今我已经不怕了
Well, I'm not scared anymore.
在你的统治下 星桥坠落 在那件事的伤疤上 人们掀起起义
On your watch, the Star Bridge fell. And from that scar insurgency was birthed.
在你的统治下 两个世界烧为灰烬
On your watch, two worlds were incinerated
完全不顾及无辜者或后果
with not a care to innocence or consequence.
在你的统治下 哈里谢顿和他的信众得以逃离
On your watch, Hari Seldon and his followers were allowed to flee.
你把一个因为任性妄为 而四分五裂的帝国交到我手上
You have bequeathed me an Empire rent by impulsive action.
我不会重蹈覆辙 在我的统治下不会这样
The same will not be said of me. Not on my watch.
我将拯救我们的功业
I would save our legacy.
兄弟
Brother…
一个早已死去的人 阴魂不散 令你无法释怀
you are haunted by the ghost of a man long dead.
我们都是如此 兄弟
We all are, Brother.
你的统治已经结束
Your watch is over.
你将留在川陀 处理你放任不管 而因此恶化的伤口
You will stay on Trantor, tending to the wounds you have allowed to fester.
走吧
Go.
把黄昏兄弟的物品送回宫殿
Return Brother Dusk's belongings to the palace.
如今帝国当然不会因莽撞行事而分崩离析
Certainly now the Empire will no longer be rent by impulsive action.
是你召唤我吗 大帝
You summoned me, Empire?
外围星域的一个通讯浮标断联了
A communications buoy has gone dark in the Outer Reach.
带上你的团队去调查
Take your team and investigate.
这就去 大帝
At once, Empire.
多尔文
Dorwin.
基地通讯的频率越来越少了
Our dispatches from the Foundation have become sporadic.
去造访他们
Pay them a visit.
提醒基地 不要对帝国有所隐瞒
And remind the Foundation that Empire will not be kept in the dark.
-那是… -情况不太妙 是吧
-Is that, uh-- -Doesn't look good, does it?
这里由谁指挥 路易斯还是你  还是玩硬币的守卫者
Who is in charge here, Lewis? You? Or is it the Warden with the coin tricks?
因为她似乎让情况变得复杂了
Because it seems she's managed to complicate matters.
-让我说清楚 猎手柯恩 -大猎手
-Let me be clear, Huntress Keaen-- -Grand Huntress.
我们面临危机的唯一原因
The only reason we have a crisis
是你们擅自入侵帝国的私人领域
is because you trespassed on the Emperor's personal domain.
如果塞佛当时带我去塔那边 把我要的东西给我
If only Salvor had taken me to the tower and given me what I'd wanted,
我们早都离开这个星球了
we'd already be off-planet.
我们慢速舰上的模组
The module from our slow ship?
你们的人又不会用它
It's not as if your people have any use for it.
你们已经困在端点星了 帝国确保这一点
You're marooned on Terminus. The Empire made sure of that.
路易斯
Lewis.
你们为何需要模组
Why do you need it?
我族人在科技上极其匮乏
My people are technologically bankrupt.
我们要灭亡了 总督
We're dying, Director.
自从帝国让我们的大气层燃烧后 我们一直苦苦挣扎
We have been ever since the Empire set our atmosphere on fire.
因为一个并非我们犯下的罪行 一半人口失去生命
Half our population lost for a crime that we were innocent of.
和你们不同 我们有飞船
Unlike you, we have ships.
我们能够离开被摧毁的世界 寻找另一个恒星系
We can leave our poisoned world, find another star system.
我们只需要在虚空中导航的工具
If only we had the means to navigate the void.
如果支援你们 帝国会摧毁我们
The Empire would crush us for assisting you.
我们这是在逼你出手相助 总督
We're forcing your hand, Director.
因为我们已经没什么可失去的了
Because we have nothing left to lose.
你无法和一个愿意将棋盘烧毁的人下棋
You can't play chess with someone who's willing to set the board on fire.
那是某种高射炮吗
Is that some kind of flak cannon?
如果他们以为那能突破围栏 那就是在浪费时间
Wasting their time if they think that's gonna penetrate the fence.
这一切都不对劲 法拉应该更高明的
None of this feels right. Phara is smarter than this.
他们摧毁了通讯浮标 他们是有备而来
They took out the comms buoy, and they came in prepared.
他们的策略比我们想的大 但我却看不出到底是什么
There's a larger strategy here, and I am missing it somehow.
不如我乘飞船离开 去其他星球求助
What if I take my ship, make a run for the stars, get help?
不行…你还没进入轨道 就会被他们从空中击落
No, no. They'd shoot you out of the sky before you ever made it into orbit.
后悔没在还来得及的时候离开了
Regretting you didn't bug out when you had the chance?
我这辈子做的傻事多了去了 塞佛哈定
Done a lot of foolish things in my life, Salvor Hardin.
陪在你身边不是其中之一
Sticking by your side is not one of them.
史上最佳男仆从
Best manservant ever.
穹窿并非出自安纳克里昂之手
The Vault isn't Anacreon…
也不是外星生物建的
or alien at all.
它一定与哈里有关
It's gotta be connected to Hari.
你怎么知道
How do you know that?
因为我昏迷时看到的画面
Because the vision I saw when I blacked out,
是川陀星 在哈里的图书馆 有个男孩拿刀指着我
it was on Trantor in Hari's library, with a boy holding a knife on me.
也许这是在警告我们远离它
What if it was a warning to stay away?
如果路易斯是对的呢
What if Lewis is right?
正如他所说的 我是异类 横冲直撞、四处捣乱
I'm an outlier, just like he says, barging around, knocking things over,
搞砸了谢顿的计划
screwing up Seldon's plan?
塞佛 如果你就是谢顿的计划呢
Salvor, what if you are Seldon's plan?
个人的命运将永远是一个谜
The fate of one individual will always remain a mystery.
守卫者 还记得我的承诺吗  夷平你的城市
Remember my promise, Warden? Razing your city to the ground?
但一群人的行动
But the movements of masses,
文化的兴起与消亡 因果与世界…
the rise and falls of cultures, causes and worlds…
对于这些问题 哈里谢顿早已解开谜底
These were answers Hari Seldon had long since unriddled.
是时候了
It's time.
如其名字所描述的 这场终结的开始
And the beginning of the end, as befitting its name,
在端点星上发生了
took place on Terminus.
字幕翻译：易晗